Guide to the Ari and Helene Bousbib Collection of Photographs 1879-1996 PR 384
New-York Historical Society
- Series II: Hollywood Studio Photography, 1915-1990
  - Subseries: RAY JONES, 1932-1947
    - Portraits P-Z, 1934-1945 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Subseries: MADISON LACY, 1937-1946
    This subseries consists of photos by Madison S. Lacy (1898-1978), an American Hollywood studio photographer active from the late 1910s to the 1970s. Subjects include actors Eddie Albert, James Cagney, Signe Hasso, Ian Hunter, Jackie Oakey, Martha Raye, and Thomas Mitchell. There are a number of publicity photos for the films "Three Cheers for the Irish," "Four Wives," and "Navy Blues." These are interfiled alphabetically by the first actor listed on the photo.
    - Portraits A-C, 1940-1943 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Portraits D-H, 1941-1946 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Portraits I-L, 1939 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Portraits M, 1939-1941 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Portraits N-R, 1939-1941 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Portraits S-Z, unidentified, 1937-1946 (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - Subseries: HARRY LANGDON, circa 1975-1990
    This subseries contains 4 boxes of oversize color photos taken by Hollywood celebrity photographer Harry Landon (1934- ). Most of the photographs are mounted on foamcore. The subjects of these photos are iconic figures of the 1970s and 1980s, including Joan Collins, Pia Zadora, Cher, Jane Fonda, Joan Rivers, Roseann Barr, Will Smith, Boy George, Diana Ross, and Ronald Reagan.
    - Portraits A-Z, circa 1975-1990 (Box 32-35)
  - Subseries: BERT LONGWORTH, 1933-1946
    This subseries contains photographs by Bert Longworth (1893-1964), a Hollywood stills photographer who worked at MGM, Paramount, Warner Bros., capturing film stars in Busby Berkeley's musicals, off-set publicity photos, and portraits.
    Among the subjects included in this subseries are Ralph Bellamy, Rudy Vallee, Irene Manning, James Stewart, Rosalind Russell, and Joe E. Brown.
    - Portraits A-Z, 1933-1946 (Box 36, Folder 1-8)
  - Subseries: JOHN MIEHLE, 1933-1947
    This subseries contains photographs taken by RKO studio photographer John Miehle (1902-1952). The photos, taken between 1933-1947, include images of actors Fred Astaire, Ralph Bellamy, Ginger Rogers, John Barrymore, Basil Rathbone, Gregory Peck, and Carole Lombard, among others.
    - Portraits A-I, 1935-1943 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Portraits J-Z, unidentified, 1933-1947 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Subseries: HAL PHYFE, 1931-1936
    This subseries contains the work of Hal Phyfe (1892-1968), great-grandson of Duncan Phyfe, the early American furniture designer. He opened his photography studio in New York in 1926, and built a reputation for his theatrical portraiture shot on commission. Most of the photos in this subseries were shot for Fox Film Corp. Subjects include the actors Sheila Barrett, Jesse Lasky, Helen Mack, Irene Ware, Peggy Ross,and Henry Fonda.
    - Portraits A-Z, 1931-1936 (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - Subseries: GENE ROBERT RICHEE, 1923-1950
    This subseries consists of photographs taken by Gene Robert Richee (1896-1972), a studio photographer who worked for Paramount Pictures from 1925 to 1935, and later worked for MGM and Warner Brothers.
    Subjects include actors Jack Benny, Dane Clark, Paul Lukas, Mary Martin, Doris Day, Bob Hope, Danny Kaye, and Richard "Skeets" Gallagher," among many others.
    - Portraits A-B, 1924-1940 (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - Portraits C, 1928-1945 (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - Portraits D-G, 1924-1949 (Box 37, Folder 3)
    - Portraits H-K, 1925-1950 (Box 37, Folder 4)
    - Portraits L, 1929-1949 (Box 37, Folder 5)
    - Portraits M-N, 1926-1953 (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Portraits O-Z, unidentified, 1923-1950 (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - Portraits Oversize, 1927-1940 (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - Subseries: A.L. WHITEY SCHAFER, 1935-1950
    This subseries contains the work of A. L. "Whitey" Schafer (1902-1951), a longtime still photographer who started working at Paramount Pictures in 1923. In 1935 Schafer was appointed head of photography at Columbia Pictures, where he was in charge of portrait, publicity, advertising and production still photography.
    Included in this subseries are photos of actors such as Joe E. Brown, Barry Fitzgerald, Joan Fontaine, and Ray Milland.
    - Portraits A-G, 1935-1947 (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - Portraits H-Z, 1935-1950 (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - Portraits Oversize, 1937-1950 (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - Subseries: BERT SIX, 1938-1955
    This subseries consists of photographs by Bert Six (1902-1967), a photographer for Warner Bros. who was best known for his glamour shots of Hollywood actresses. Six began his career at Warner Bros. in 1934, and became head of the still department in 1945.
    Included here are photographs of actors including Bette Davis, Joan Fontaine, Joan Crawford, Eve Arden, and Jack Benny.
    - Portraits A-B, 1941-1948 (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - Portraits C, 1948-1954 (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - Portraits D, 1938-1955 (Box 38, Folder 5)
    - Portraits E-L, 1938-1949 (Box 38, Folder 6)
    - Portraits M-O, 1940-1951 (Box 38, Folder 7)
    - Portraits P-Z, 1938-1952 (Box 38, Folder 8)
  - Subseries: SCOTTY WELBOURNE, 1933-1944
    This subseries contains the work of Scotty Welbourne (1907-1979), a still photographer who began his Hollywood career in the 1930s, and was head of photography at Warner Bros. form 1941-1948. In the 1950s, Welbourne shifted to cinematography, and worked in television for the duration of his career.
    Subjects of this subseries include actors Charles Boyer, Billie Burke, Joe E. Brown, Jack Benny, Bette Davis, Joan Fontaine, Henry Fonda, Irene Hervey, Ian Hunter, Ida Lupino, Fred MacMurray, Frank Shields, and Doris Weston, among many others.
    - Portraits A-L, 1933-1944 (Box 39, Folder 1-7)
    - Portraits M-Z, 1935-1944 (Box 40, Folder 1-5)
    - Portraits Oversize, 1939 (Box 42, Folder 5)
  - Subseries: WITZEL STUDIOS, 1915-1927
    This subseries contains photographs produced by Witzel Studios, founded in Los Angeles by photographer Albert Walter Witzel (1879–1929) in 1909. As Hollywood became the new center of the motion picture industry, demand for Witzel's portrait work grew as film studios sought to promote their movies with glamorous portraits and publicity shots of their stars.
    This subseries includes images of early film actors such as Betty Brice, Anna Held, George Larkin, Wallace Reid, and Marin Sais.
    - Portraits A-Z, 1915-1927 (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - Subseries: MISCELLANEOUS and unidentified Hollywood studio photographers, 1926-1967
    This subseries consists of miscellaneous photographs grouped together by collector and labeled "Lost Hollywood."
    Subjects include: Eve Arden, Lionel Barrymore, Gary Cooper, Audrey Hepburn, Katharine Hepburn, Claudette Colbert, Marlene Dietrich, Bette Davis, Greta Garbo.
    Photographers include: Jack Albin, Mack Elliot, Bud Fraker, Ruth Harriet Louise, Sy Siedman, Melbourne Spurr, St. Hilaire, and Len Weissman.
    - Portraits A-D, 1928-1950 (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Portraits E-H, 1926-1960 (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Portraits J-Q, 1932-1957 (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - Portraits R-Z, unidentified, 1935-1950 (Box 41, Folder 4)
    - Portraits Oversize, 1928-1967 (Box 42, Folder 6-7)
- Series III: Photojournalism and Documentary Photography, 1880-1996
  This series contains a diverse range of work dating from 1880 to 1996. It includes the work of photojournalists Rudolph Arnold, Margaret Bourke-White, John Florea, Philippe Halsman, Jill Freedman, Mary Ellen Mark, Fred McDarrah, and Ken Regan, who each documented various aspects of American life and culture in the 20th century. The work of celebrity photographers and paparazzi such as Peter Basch, Andre De Dienes, and Ron Galella is also part of this series. In addition, the series includes the work of various photography studios that specialized in subjects such as advertising and store windows (Artkraft Strauss, Worsinger) and architecture and construction (Eugene de Salignac, Wurts Bros., George P. Hall and Son). Photos from newsphoto agencies (Magnum, Acme Newspictures Inc, PM News), press departments (New York World's Fair) and government agencies (White House Photography, WPA) are also included here.
  - Subseries: ACME NEWSPICTURES, 1945
    This subseries consists of photographs of the aftermath of the plane crash that occurred on July 28, 1945. A B25 plane crashed into the Empire State Building.
    - Empire State Building plane crash, 1945 (Box 44, Folder 1-4)
  - Subseries: RUDOLPH ARNOLD, 1931-1939
    This subseries contains photographs taken by Rudolph Arnold (1902-1966). After studying at the New York School of Photography, Arnold worked at the New York Graphic, where he started to focus on aviation photography. In 1928, Arnold started his own aviation photography business and worked out of the following New York air fields and airports during his career: Roosevelt Field, the old Curtiss Airport, Floyd Bennett Field, and LaGuardia Airport. He also did motion-picture camera work for Universal and Paramount.
    The photographs in this subseries were taken at Floyd Bennett Field in Brooklyn, NY between 1931-1939. The majority of these images are of aircraft manufactured by Grumman, Douglas, Lockheed and Curtiss. In addition, the collection contains images Arnold took of aviation personalities including Douglas (Wrong Way) Corrigan, Amelia Earhart, and Howard Hughes.
    - Aviation at Floyd Bennett Field, Brooklyn NY, 1931-1939 (Box 44, Folder 5-7)
  - Subseries: ARTKRAFT STRAUSS STUDIO, 1917-1940
    This subseries contains photographs documenting the work of the Artkraft Strauss Sign Corporation. Artkraft Strauss was one of New York City's preeminent sign designers and manufacturers, responsible for creating some of the most iconic signs in American advertising. The company was particularly known for their "spectaculars," which were giant illuminated signs, often incorporating special effects and moving parts.
    This subseries contains images of the company's signs, as well as their fabrication and installation. Artkraft Strauss' employees and facilities are also featured. One group of photos documents the fabrication and installation of a 1936 Times Square "spectacular" ad for Wrigley's gum featuring fish blowing bubbles. Unfortunately, the collection does not include an image of the finished product.
    Related Materials
    The Album File contains a album documenting Artkraft Strauss' creation and installation of the Pepsi Cola "spectacular" electric sign in Times Square.
    Call number: PR 02 Volume 472
    - Billboards, 1917-1940, undated (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - Studio Interiors and Fabrication, 1936 (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - Subseries: BACHRACH STUDIOS, 1880-1945
    The Bachrach family has been in the commercial photography business for more than 140 years. David Bachrach (1845-1921) founded Bachrach Studios in 1868. His son Louis Fabian Bachrach (1881-1963) began his photographic career by working with his father in Washington and Baltimore and by helping several photographers in New York. Louis Fabian Bachrach, Jr. (1917-2010), known as Fabian Bachrach, introduced color photography to the studio in the 1950s, while his brother Bradford (1910 or 1911-1992) headed the company until 1978. Fabian's son Robert now (2017) heads the family business, while son Louis Fabian Bachrach III has his own independent portrait studio.
    This series consists of two photograph albums. One is the album of Louis Fabian Bachrach (1881-1963), and contains formal portraits and snapshots of his family, as well of the offices and employees of his photographic studio. The second album contains photographs of Louis Fabian Bachrach's mother, Fanny Keyser Bachrach (1854-1937), throughout her life. It appears to have been assembled by her children after her death.
    - Louis Fabian Bachrach album, 1900-1945 (Box 46)
    - Fanny Keyser Bachrach album, 1880-1937 (Box 47)
  - Subseries: PETER BASCH, 1950-1965
    This subseries contains the work of American photographer Peter Basch (1921–2004), known for his images of celebrities and artists in America and Europe. His photos appeared in major magazines such as Life, Look and Playboy.
    Included here are images of Jim Henson, Mitzi Gaynor, Fred Gwynn, Rock Hudson, Tuesday Weld, Harry Belafonte, dancers Pauline Koner and Jose Limon, and a series of female nudes.
    - Portraits A-Z, unidentified, 1950-1965 (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - Subseries: MARGARET BOURKE-WHITE, 1946
    This subseries contains photographs by Margaret Bourke-White (1904—1971), an American photographer known for her extensive contributions to photojournalism, particularly for her Life magazine work. She is recognized as having been the first female documentary photographer to be accredited by and work with the U.S armed forces.
    This subseries consists of photos that capture the action centered around a single park bench during the course of one day. These images were published in Look Magazine on April 30, 1946.
    - Park Bench photographs, 1946 (Box 44, Folder 8)
  - Subseries: ANDRE DE DIENES, 1945-1953
    This subseries consists of early portraits of the actress Marilyn Monroe taken by Hungarian-American fashion photographer André de Dienes (1913-1985).
    - Portraits - Marilyn Monroe, 1945-1953 (Box 48, Folder 2-4)
  - Subseries: EUGENE DE SALIGNAC, 1913-1922
    This subseries contains cyanotype photographs of the construction of the Manhattan Bridge. They are the works of Eugene de Salignac (1861–1943), an American photographer who worked for the Department of Bridges/Plant and Structures in New York City from 1906 to 1934. During this time, de Salignac documented the creation of the city's modern infrastructure—including bridges, major municipal buildings, roads and subways. His most famous image is that of painters posing nonchalantly on the cables of the Brooklyn Bridge. His negatives and vintage prints are held by the New York City Municipal Archives.
    - Manhattan Bridge Construction Cyanotypes, 1913-1922 (Box 44, Folder 9-12)
  - Subseries: FASHION PHOTOGRAPHY, 1988-1996
    This subseries contains photographs of the 1990s supermodels Gisele Bundchen, Naomi Campbell, Linda Evangelista, Kate Moss, Claudia Schiffer, and Christy Turlington. The photos are the work of various photographers, including Herb Ritts; most of the photos feature Kate Moss.
    - Supermodels, 1988-1996 (Box 49)
  - Subseries: JOHN FLOREA, 1941-1947
    This subseries consists of photos documenting World WarII, taken by John Florea (1916-2000). Florea was a staff photographer at Life who became a war correspondent during World War II. As one of America's first war photographers for the Pacific theater, he covered the Marines and the Navy, especially during the battle of Tarawa in December 1943. Later, from 1944 until the end of the war, he followed the American army in Europe, photographing the fights in France or Belgium, the destruction of the German cities, and the liberation of the concentration camps in Germany.
    - World War II photos, 1941-1947 (Box 50-51)
  - Subseries: JILL FREEDMAN, 1969-1986
    This subseries contains the work of documentary photographer Jill Freedman (1939-2019). Freedman immersed herself in the world of her subjects, which included the Beatty-Cole circus performers, New York City police officers and firefighters, and New York City street life [includes explicit images taken at sex clubs].
    - Circus Days, 1975 (Box 52, Folder 1)
    - Firehouse, 1977 (Box 52, Folder 2-3)
    - Street Cops, 1981 (Box 52, Folder 4-5)
    - Street Scenes, 1969-1986 (Box 53, Folder 1-4)
  - Subseries: RON GALELLA, 1978-1992
    This subseries consists of photographs by Ron Galella (1931-) an American photographer considered a pioneer paparazzo. Galella's celebrity photographs have appeared in many major publications including Vanity Fair, Time, and People. This subseries contains images of Imogene Coca, Gloria Swanson, Johnny Carson, Steven Spielberg, Lana Turner, Madonna, Bruce Springsteen, Tom Cruise, Brad Pitt, among others.
    - Celebrity Photographs A-Z, 1978-1992 (Box 44, Folder 13-14)
  - Subseries: GEORGE P. HALL AND SON, 1894-1898
    This subseries contains 10 photographs by renowned New York City photography firm George P. Hall and Son documenting the construction of the Manhattan Speedway, 1894-1898. It includes views of the High Bridge Aqueduct and Water Tower.
    New-York Historical Society Library also holds a collection of Hall photographs:
    PR 24 George P. Hall and Son Photograph Collection, ca. 1876-ca. 1914.
    - Construction of the Manhattan Speedway, 1894-1898 (Box 48, Folder 5)
  - Subseries: PHILIPPE HALSMAN, 1953-1975
    This subseries contains photos taken by Philippe Halsman (1906-1979), an American portrait photographer whose work was featured on the covers and pages of magazines such as Life, Look, Esquire, and the Saturday Evening Post. Images included here feature unidentified domestic scenes, and portraits of prominent businessmen and journalists.
    - Group Portraits, circa 1960 (Box 48, Folder 6)
    - Portraits, 1953-1975 (Box 48, Folder 7)
  - Subseries: MAGNUM, 1980-1988
    This subseries contains photographs by members of Magnum, an international photographic cooperative. Images include New York City street scenes; images of Ronald Reagan and Walter Mondale campaigning in 1980; Woody Allen on set; Madonna; and the 1986 International PEN Convention.
    - Photographs, 1980-1988 (Box 44, Folder 15)
  - Subseries: MARY ELLEN MARK, 1986-1987
    This subseries contains color portraits of children and teenagers taken in 1986-1987 by Mary Ellen Mark (1940-2015), an American documentary photographer.
    - Portraits, 1986-1987 (Box 54, Folder 1)
  - Subseries: FRED MCDARRAH, 1956-1995
    This subseries contains the work of Village Voice photojournalist Fred McDarrah (1926-2007). During his 50-year career at The Voice, McDarrah covered politics, art, the rock music scene, dance, entertainment, and demonstrations in support of the peace movement, gay liberation, and welfare and civil rights.
    McDarrah documented the galleries, lofts, cafes, bars and streets of Greenwich Village and Soho, and the artists, actors, musicians, Beat poets, writers and counterculture figures who populated them. Photographs of these people and places, taken during the 1960s through the 1980s, make up the bulk of this series.
    McDarrah also focused his lens on the world of New York politics. This series contains images of politicians such as Alfonse D'Amato, Elizabeth Holtzman, John Lindsay, and Charles Rangel, among many others. Also included are images of protests and activists such as Angela Davis, Abbie Hoffman and Jane Jacobs, among others.
    Other images of note include scenes from the 1977 Blackout; a beatnik birthday party for Ted Joans; a Star Trek convention; and the NAMES Project AIDS Memorial Quilt
    This series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
    - Artists and the Art World, 1959-1992, undated (Box 56, Folder 1-5)
      Contains photographs of artists and New York art world figures. This includes, but is not limited to, artists such as Louise Nevelson, Mary Miss, Richard Avedon, Marisol Escobar, David Hockney, Larry Rivers, Robert Rauschenberg; museum executives and gallery ownerslike Tom Armstrong and Leo Castelli; museum exhibitions and installations at the Met Museum, MOMA, the Whitney, and Soho art galleries; and images of works by artists such as Hans Haacke, Joseph Levy, and Keith Haring.
    - Composers, Conductors, and Musicians, 1959-1977, undated (Box 56, Folder 6)
      Includes photos of Otis Blackwell, David Bowie, Betty Carter, Leonard Cohen, Judy Collins, Alice Cooper, David Del Tredici, Bob Dylan, Dizzy Gillespie, Jimi Hendrix, Billie Holiday, Mick Jagger, Grace Jones, Patti La Belle, Barry Manilow, Bette Midler, Thea Musgrave, Elvis Presley, Lou Rawls, Smokey Robinson, Sonny Rollins, Pete Seeger, Frank Sinatra, and the Who, among many others
    - Events, 1956-1978, undated (Box 56, Folder 7)
      World's Fair 1964; 1977 Blackout; Bryant Park Book Fair; Coney Island Beach clean up; events at MOMA; parades, outdoor art shows, festivals, and concerts; NYU graduation ceremony; parties, including an Artist's Club New Year's Eve party and a beatnik birthday party for Ted Joans; Star Trek convention; Polar Bears swimmers.
    - Film and Theater, 1959-1981, undated (Box 56, Folder 8-9)
      includes actors and directors. Actors: Woody Allen, Jim Belushi, Jackie Collins, Barbara Cook, Tony Curtis, Bette Davis, Robert DeNiro, Divine, Jane Fonda, Lillian Gish, Dustin Hoffman, William Holden, Louise Lasser, Paul Mazursky, Liza Minelli, Jeanne Moreau, Paul Newman, Sidney Poitier, Robert Redford, Chita Rivera, Roy Rogers, Susan Sarandon, Sissy Spacek, Meryl Streep, David Susskind, Tommy Tune Directors: Bertrand Blier, Milos Forman, Alfred Hitchcock, Ted Kotcheff, Joseph Papp, Jan Troell
    - New York City Street Scenes, 1959-1978, undated (Box 57, Folder 1-8)
      Contains photographs taken in various neighborhoods around New York City from the late 1950s through the 1970s. Some record the vitality of street vendors, crowds, parks, and night clubs, as well as children playing in the street. Other photos focus on specific buildings and architectural details, or scenes of urban blight.
      The photos have been arranged by subject: aerial views; architectural details and statuary; landmarks (City Hall, Empire State Building, Jefferson Market, Radio City Music Hall, Rockefeller Center); markets and store fronts; museums and parks; night clubs and taverns; street life; and urban blight
    - Politicians, 1965-1993, undated (Box 57, Folder 9-13)
      photos of politicians, mostly New York City-based. Includes Bella Abzug, Herman Badillo, Mario Biaggi, Hugh Carey, Mario Cuomo, Alfonse D'Amato, David Dinkins, Gerald and Betty Ford, Elizabeth Holzman, John Lindsay, Bess Meyerson, Daniel Patrick Moynihan, Nelson Rockefeller, Andrew Stein, and Robert Wagner, among others.
    - Portraits, General, 1965-1978 (Box 57, Folder 14)
      includes photos of Floyd Abrams, John Artis, Stanley Fisher, Harry Helmsley, Margaret Mead, Rev. Sun Yung Moon, Tiger Morse, Howard Stein, and others.
    - Protests and Activism, 1960-1992, undated (Box 57, Folder 15)
      Contains photographs of political protests, including an anti-war protest at the Pentagon in 1967, the Democratic National Convention protests in Chicago 1968, and the NAMES Project AIDS Memorial Quilt in Washington D.C. in 1992. In addition, there are photos of activists including Angela Davis, Abbie Hoffman, Jane Jacobs, Aron Kay (the "Yippie pie thrower") and others.
    - Views Outside of New York City, 1970, undated (Box 56, Folder 10)
      Albany, NY; Warwick NY; Newark, NJ
    - Writers, 1959-1978, undated (Box 56, Folder 11-12)
      Contains photographs of authors, journalists, and cultural critics. Some of these writers include: Amiri Baraka, Brendan Behan, Bonnie Bremser, Jimmy Breslin, William F. Buckley, William Burroughs, Truman Capote, Pete Hamill, Joseph Heller, Lillian Hellman, Fran Lebowitz, and Tom Wolfe. Also included are televison journalists such as Steve Dunleavy, Dan Rather and Rose Ann Scamardella, and TV news executive Roger Ailes.
    - Unidentified and Miscellaneous, 1971, undated (Box 57, Folder 16)
  - Subseries: NEW YORK WORLD'S FAIR PRESS DEPT., 1939